- [Narrator] Imagine a
small rural village in Iraq
in the middle of the night in 2003.
A man is hiding inside
an underground hole.
Its entrance covered with styrofoam.
And suddenly, the streetlights
in the entire village go out
and hundreds of U.S. soldiers
begin sweeping through the town.
As the troops reach the farmhouse,
a soldier starts to unearth a rope,
discovering that it leads
to the hidden trap door.
They open it and prepare to
throw a grenade into the hole
just to be safe.
But just before the pin is pulled,
everyone freezes as a pair of
hands emerge from the hole,
followed by a bearded man.
With his hands in the air, he
declares to those around him.
"My name is Saddam Hussein.
I am the president of Iraq
and I want to negotiate."
- Ladies and gentlemen, we got him.
(gentle music)
- [Narrator] Whether
you've heard the story
of Saddam's hiding place
because of the countless
memes circulating online,
or whether you lived through this time
and think you remember it,
I doubt you ever heard the full story.
And so for this video, I
will be exploring just that.
This is how Saddam Hussein was found.
(dramatic music)
The hunt for Saddam began
with the invasion of Iraq
in March of 2003.
- My fellow citizens, at this hour,
American and coalition forces
are in the early stages
of military operations to
disarm Iraq, to free its people,
and to defend the world from grave danger.
- [Narrator] The U.S.
had started a coalition
to overthrow the Iraqi president,
and the reason they presented
to the world for doing so
was that they claimed Saddam
was hiding weapons of mass destruction.
- There is no doubt that Saddam Hussein
now has weapons of mass destruction.
- [Narrator] A claim that would
later turn out to be false.
- You know, when we first got in there
and started looking around
and didn't find anything,
get that kinda sinking feeling that uh-oh.
(suspenseful music)
- [Narrator] The invasion itself went fast
as the United States, along
with troops from the U.K.,
Australia, and Poland fought their way
to the capital city of Baghdad,
which fell just three weeks
after the initial invasion.
But still, the troops were not able
to find the Iraqi
president, Saddam Hussein.
- [Reporter] To the very heart of Baghdad,
U.S. tanks and troops finally arrive,
spelling the end for the Iraqi regime.
The next task, to hunt down the men
who fought and defended
the city for a fortnight.
- [Narrator] And in the middle
of a public square in the city,
American forces join Iraqis
near a massive statue
dedicated to Saddam, whose
rule has come to an end.
And to declare their victory,
American soldiers placed an American flag
over the face of the statue.
This was much to the dismay
of the Iraqi citizens
who had gathered with them,
as raising an American flag
seemed to represent the U.S.
controlling the Iraqi people.
And after realizing
the image this created,
the soldiers quickly replaced
their flag with an Iraqi one,
and then the statue was toppled.
(crowd cheering)
But though his likeness
was brought to the ground,
the real Saddam was still at large.
Locating him and other high
ranking members of his regime
became a top priority
for the U.S. military.
And to keep track of the
targeted former officials,
a special deck of playing cards is created
that features the 52
most wanted officials.
This way, soldiers who regularly
play games during breaks
will be able to easily
pick up high value targets
and recognize the faces
of those on the hunt.
And Saddam Hussein remains
priority number one,
the Ace of Spades, along
with his sons, Uday and Qusay
right below him.
- [Reporter] In the
skies and on the ground
they have one order, to find Saddam.
The word is he never stays in one place
for more than a few hours,
constantly on the move probably by car.
- [Narrator] Several months
pass after the fall of Baghdad.
And many targets are
found and apprehended,
but none of them lead the U.S.
to where Saddam or his sons are hiding.
To gather more information,
a $15 million bounty was
placed on each brother,
and a $25 million bounty
was put forth for Saddam.
- Senator, is today's $25
million on the head of Saddam
gonna change anything?
- [Reporter] With a reward of $25 million,
American troops are increasingly confident
that they will soon have
the ace in their pack.
- [Narrator] And this incentive
gives the American military
the exact break they had been looking for
as four months after the start of the war,
a man enters a military base in Mosul,
claiming that he's sheltering
Uday and Qusay in his home.
(suspenseful music)
Almost unable to believe it,
troops are dispatched the
next day to the man's house
located in Mosul, the
second largest city of Iraq.
And to their surprise,
Saddam's sons, Uday and Qusay
are actually inside the
building, hiding in a mansion
that is now being
surrounded by U.S. troops.
And as the brothers are not
willing to come quietly,
gunfire breaks out.
The U.S. troops retreat
and call in reinforcements.
Not only do they get additional manpower,
but also a missile strike
is called on the house
the brothers are hiding in,
destroying most of the house.
And after the dust is cleared,
soldiers are able to enter the house,
but the brothers had already been killed.
- Everybody agrees that
it would've been better
if the brothers had been captured alive.
- I would never consider this a failure.
Our mission is to find, kill or capture.
(gentle techno music)
- [Narrator] Even though
it is perhaps unlikely
his sons would've given any
information to the Americans
about where Saddam is hiding,
with both of them gone,
the road to finding him remains unclear.
But what the raid on the safe house did
is it triggered Saddam to
release a sign of life himself
as an audio tape surfaces and is broadcast
on which Saddam can be heard mourning
the loss of his two sons.
(Saddam speaking in foreign language)
- [Narrator] The existence of this tape
confirms that Saddam is still alive.
And the other thing this
whole situation showed
is that the bounty had resulted
in someone coming forward
and providing helpful information.
- Secretary Powell today
approved the payment
of $30 million reward to the individual
who provided the critical
piece of information.
- [Narrator] Therefore, the U.S. decides
to pay the full reward to the informant.
$30 million in addition to being relocated
to the United States.
Their hope is that once Iraqi citizens
see that the U.S. is serious
about their bounties,
it would encourage more people
to step forward with information.
- We're trying to look for Saddam Hussein.
We have his two sons and we
already took care of them,
but we need Saddam Hussein.
We're urging the Iraqi people
to help us out any way that they can.
- [Reporter] There's no
shortage of information.
But with a $25 million reward
on offer, much is unreliable.
- [Narrator] But as the months rolled by
with many unsuccessful
raids to capture Saddam,
it begins to seem less and less likely
that anyone will come forward.
(door thudding)
- [Reporter 1] Three civilians were shot
during last night's raid.
Innocent victims of this frantic search.
- [Reporter 2] An elite secretive unit
known as Task Force 20
is leading the hunt.
There is no clear indication tonight
that his capture is imminent.
- The Americans are not about
to apologize for all of this.
- [Reporter 1] A trail of
destruction left in the wake
of the special task force
that's hunting down Saddam Hussein.
(soft percussive music)
- [Narrator] With many of the raids
leading to absolutely nothing,
the focus again shifts.
And the U.S. military puts their attention
towards completing the
deck by tracking down
prior officials from Saddam's regime.
Several high ranking officials
that worked directly
under Saddam were captured
with the hope that they might be able
to provide information.
Surprisingly though,
none of them can point
to their former president's hiding place.
And while the bulk of the
military remained focused
on hunting targets from the deck of cards,
one Staff Sergeant Eric Maddox
decides to go into a
completely different direction.
Maddox realizes that the
targets they are focused on
represent the old regime
that had fallen from power.
These are people that were given positions
because they were related to Saddam,
and so their power came from him.
Right now, what Saddam needs is people
with the power to protect him,
and that can only come from
one place, his bodyguards.
While in power, Saddam had a
system of personal protection
comprised of three different tiers.
The outermost level of guards
were assigned to fixed locations,
such as his various
palaces across the country.
Above them was a level of guards
that would travel ahead of Saddam
to secure locations in various areas.
And finally, above these
guards were the Hamaya,
the innermost layer of elite guards.
Those who would stay
with Saddam at all times.
Maddox theorizes that these guards
are likely the ones
currently protecting Saddam.
And in order to find them,
he begins his work in
Tikrit, Saddam's hometown.
Tikrit had already been
thoroughly searched
and it is largely believed
that Saddam isn't hiding here.
However, it is still a hotbed
for another family group, the Al-Muslit.
And most of Saddam's elite bodyguards
came from exactly this family.
As Maddox begins his interrogations,
he notices that one name keeps popping up.
Muhammad Ibrahim Omar Al-Muslit.
And the more Maddox learns
about Muhammad Ibrahim,
the more convinced he feels
that he is on the right track.
Not only was Muhammad Ibrahim
one of Saddam's most trusted
inner circle bodyguards,
but it seems like he is currently leading
the entire resistance
against the U.S. occupation.
He had installed several lieutenants
in charge of certain areas of Iraq
to coordinate attacks
against coalition forces.
And he is the one coordinating
funds for counter attacks.
- [Reporter] Saddam's loyalists here
had taken off their uniforms
and tried to fight the
Marines with guerilla tactics.
- [Narrator] And if Muhammad Ibrahim
is really running operations
in Saddam's stead,
then he has to know
where Saddam is hiding.
And so, Muhammad Ibrahim
becomes a prime target.
To get to him, Maddox Interrogates
a nephew of Muhammad Ibrahim,
who then reveals the names and locations
of two close business associates,
as well as the name of
Muhammad's driver, Basim Latif.
Basim along with family members
of these business
associates are interrogated
and the U.S. is able to
begin filling in the gaps
of Muhammad's movement.
So far that they even find out
the location of Muhammad's son, Muslit,
who is interrogated next.
Initially, it seems that Muslit
isn't able to be of much help.
He didn't have much
involvement in the resistance,
but what he did reveal
is that he used to often
go fishing with his father.
And even though they don't go anymore,
he knows that his father still fishes
at a pond he owns in the city of Samarra.
This may seem like a trivial
piece of information,
but Maddox thought back to an
interrogation he had before
with a prior housekeeper of Saddam.
He remembers that the housekeeper
had mentioned that Saddam loved Masgouf,
a type of fish that is popular in Iraq.
Suddenly, the trail seemed red hot
and Maddox was certain that Muhammad
would be able to lead him to Saddam.
(bright lilting music)
To find out more, U.S.
forces raid the fish farm
Muhammad was known to use.
Two fishermen were located,
but neither of them were Muhammad.
And when these fishermen are questioned,
Maddox finds out that
one of them was a cousin
to a lieutenant in the resistance.
And the fisherman also
mentions an uncle they shared
who had a house in Baghdad.
Perhaps Muhammad could be hiding there.
If so, he would be hiding in plain sight
in the Iraqi capital of Baghdad
that had been under the control
of the U.S. led coalition for months.
But with no better lead to follow,
the decision is made to
raid the house in Baghdad.
When you think about it,
what led them here is a
series of rather weak links.
As U.S. troops are about
to raid an apartment
of an uncle of a fisherman from a place
where the son of the suspect
remembers fishing with his dad.
And so, it comes as a
surprise to the special forces
when inside the apartment
they find their suspect.
Muhammad Ibrahim Omar
Al-Muslit is captured.
(helicopter blades whirring)
Still, there was no guarantee
that Muhammad would be willing to talk.
Maddox himself questions him
and he offers him protection
for himself and his family.
And with that assurance,
Muhammad begins to talk
and he reveals that Saddam is hiding
in the small farming village of Ad-Dawr,
bringing us back to the scene
from the very beginning of this video.
As the U.S. troops searched a town,
Muhammad Ibrahim is there
with them as a prisoner.
Based on his information,
they search two unassuming farmhouses
just east of the Tigris River.
But when both of them are searched,
their target is still nowhere in sight.
Beginning to think this
rate is just a dead end,
the troops are about to give up.
But then, Muhammad Ibrahim
points out another building
just to the north of the second farmhouse.
The building is little more
than a shack with two rooms,
and no one is inside here either.
It seems as though Muhammad Ibrahim
has a good idea of where Saddam is,
but the soldiers are not catching on.
And there must have been
some final mental block
that prevents Muhammad Ibrahim
from straight up telling them.
He is willing to help, but he
also doesn't wanna be the one
giving Saddam away directly.
And so, Muhammad Ibrahim begins
kicking at a piece of rope
half buried in the ground outside the hut.
Now, the soldiers understand.
They find the trap door and Saddam.
- Ladies and gentlemen, we got him.
(crowd cheering and applauding)
- United States military forces
captured Saddam Hussein alive.
In the history of Iraq, a
dark and painful era is over.
A hopeful day has arrived.
(screen whooshing)
(somber music)
- [Narrator] Even though
Saddam Hussein was captured,
it didn't end the Iraq War.
Coalition forces had no exit strategy
once Saddam's reign had ended
and instability continued for years
as the country struggled to rebuild
what the invasion had destroyed.
The image of Saddam hiding though
became one of the most iconic
ones in modern history,
ingrained not just in the
timeline of global events,
but also in pop culture.
It even became somewhat of a
meme with people finding Saddam
hiding in all kinds of random places.
Wikipedia even struggled with vandalism
as Saddam kept hiding in
all kinds of random graphs.
But this is where it is
important to remember
that this moment didn't
become iconic by itself.
(gentle spirited music)
After Saddam was captured in this hole,
the U.S. military invited
lots of journalists
to tour his hiding place,
ensuring the world saw where
Saddam had been cowering.
- Today, I had the chance to clamber
into the tyrant's last hiding place.
It's a miserable hiding place,
particularly for a man who built
some of the most ostentatious
palaces in the Middle East.
- [Narrator] They publicized
photos of his arrest,
showing him frail and utterly defeated.
They also conducted a medical
examination of Saddam,
where a doctor checked his teeth
as though his dental hygiene was a concern
after his capture.
But this video also was released publicly.
And really, this story isn't
just about finding Saddam.
It is also a tale of the
power of different narratives.
On the U.S. side, there is the narrative
that there were weapons
of mass destruction
later proven to be false.
Both the U.S. and Saddam
understood that images
can carry immense power.
Saddam had spent decades
fostering a cult of personality,
saturating the country with his image,
using state-controlled media
to build a larger than life persona
while brutally oppressing
any form of opposition.
And the U.S. military felt
a need to erode that myth.
With the support for
the war quickly waning
both in the U.S. and globally,
an easy solution was to make
Saddam the face of the war.
Saddam was undeniably one
of the most brutal leaders
of the modern era,
and the image he projected
was built on propaganda.
But the carefully staged
presentation of his downfall,
the fact that this very
image became so well known
was no less a form of such.
(gentle somber music)
Telling stories like this is at the core
of what I try to do with this channel.
Revisiting events that shaped our world
and recreating how
exactly they played out.
And it is precisely what
I did for my next video,
focusing on the Deep
Water Horizon catastrophe.
- On April 20th, an
explosion ripped through
BP Deep Water Horizon drilling rig.
(explosion booming)
- Far offshore, the rig is
still burning out of control.
- It's the worst oil
spill in U.S. history.
- [Narrator] For this video,
I have created extensive 3D
animations to better visualize
the sheer amount of oil
lost during the disaster.
And the video explains how
engineers try to pluck a hole
more than 5,000 feet deep in the ocean.
- Because there's never been a
leak this size at this depth,
stopping it has tested the
limits of human technology.
(bell clanging)
- [Narrator] One month from now,
this video will come to YouTube,
but you can already watch
it right now on Nebula.
That is because I publish all
my videos to Nebula first.
One video ahead of the YouTube uploads.
And I created an entire video series
that is completely exclusive to Nebula
called "Under Exposure."
It is a show I am incredibly proud of
as I was able to focus
on darker subject matters
that would otherwise risk
getting demonetized on YouTube.
For example, if you enjoyed
this video about Saddam Hussein,
you will probably also
enjoy my exclusive video
about the Kuwaiti Oil Fires.
An unbelievable story of what happened
when Saddam Hussein's troops
set thousands of oil wells on fire
in the neighboring country of Kuwait.
And besides my original series,
Nebula is filled with exclusive content
from lots and lots of talented creators.
With exclusive game shows,
full length documentaries,
and even feature films.
So, sign up on nebula.tv/neo.
And if you use this link,
you will actually get a 40%
discount of the annual plan.
That comes out to just $3 a
month to access all of Nebula
where you can watch all my videos early.
So, thanks for your support
and thanks for watching.
(gentle rhythmic music)